原视频名：Blue Origin's Rockets and Rocket Engines
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/tu34znIF4oM
原视频发布日期：20210123
字幕翻译/压制：旋火，校对：我住你家楼下我姓黄，新鸽伦大火箭
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Last week Blue Origin completed the 14th test flight
上周蓝色起源完成了第14次
of their reusable sub-orbital launch vehicle and capsule New Shepard.
他们的可重复使用的亚轨道运载火箭和载人舱新谢泼德的试飞
And this was actually a new vehicle for both the capsule and the booster.
这次试飞实际上使用了全新的载人舱和助推器
It's only the fourth booster they've built in this program.
这只是他们在这个项目中建造的第四个助推器
And as I understand it there's a pretty good chance they will be carrying passengers later this year
据我所知 他们很有可能在今年晚些时候搭载乘客
while of course in parallel they're still working on their New Glenn launch vehicle
同时 他们还在研制新格伦运载火箭
which is going to be absolutely massive.
而这将绝对是庞大的
Blue Origin is of course Jeff Bezos rocket company
蓝色起源当然是那个Jeff Bezos的火箭公司
and that of course brings parallels to SpaceX.
这当然会给SpaceX带来相似之处
You've got your pair of tech billionaires spending money building rocket ships
有这么一对科技领域的亿万富翁在花钱造火箭和飞船
because that's what was cool when they were growing up.
因为在他们成长的过程中 这才是最酷的
But Blue Origin was actually founded before SpaceX.
但其实蓝色起源成立的时间比SpaceX还要早
It's been around a lot longer.
它已经存在很久了
And yet it's still only doing this suborbital thing.
但它目前还只是在做亚轨道的东西
The company's motto is gratitum ferociter right.
公司的座右铭是gratitum ferociter (拉丁语) 对吧
Step by step ferociously.
意思是一步步凶猛地发展
But their development has sort of taken a different tack.
但他们的发展却采取了不同的策略
They've started by building very small rocket engines
他们从制造非常小的火箭发动机开始
and building up and developing technological experience.
并积累和发展技术经验
The first engines they built were the BE-1.
他们制造的第一台发动机是BE-1
And these are hydrogen peroxide engines.
而这些都是过氧化氢发动机
The hydrogen peroxide decomposes to oxygen and steam
双氧水分解成氧气和蒸汽
and it's sort of the first project that a lot of people do when they're learning to build rockets.
这也是很多人在学习建造火箭时的第一个项目
Peter Beck of Rocket Lab if you remember built a rocket bike powered by these things.
火箭实验室的Peter Beck 如果你还记得的话 他造了一辆由这些东西驱动的火箭自行车
The BE-1 had a thrust of about one tonne
BE-1的推力约为1吨
and they used nine of them to fly their first test vehicle
他们用其中的九台发动机驱动第一枚测试火箭
and demonstrating not only ascent but descent and soft landing
并验证了上升 下降 还有软着陆
and this is a sort of theme that we've seen with all of Blue Origins vehicles.
这也是我们在所有蓝色起源运载火箭上看到的一种主题
Blue Origin have never built a launch vehicle without recovery and reuse capability.
蓝色起源从未制造过没有回收和重复使用能力的运载火箭
The BE-2 was their next step up.
BE-2是他们的下一步发展
this was a pump fed engine.
这是一个泵循环发动机
It used peroxide and RP-1 liquid propellants.
它使用过氧化物和RP-1液体推进剂
It generated about 14 tons of thrust
产生了大约14吨的推力
and they fit five of them onto a test vehicle called the PM2.
他们把其中的5台装进了一枚叫PM2的测试火箭中
So yeah this is some footage from their very first test flight.
所以这是他们第一次试飞的一些视频
It was a short hop.
这是一个短暂的跳跃
They only lit three of the engines on ascent
他们在上升时只点燃了三台发动机
and then shut down to two of the engines for descent
然后下降时只点燃两台发动机
but even then they still have to have throttle capabilities to be able to do this.
但即使如此 他们仍然必须有节流能力才能做到这一点
Now on the second flight they lit all five engines and they wanted to start picking up speed.
那么在第二次飞行时 他们点燃了所有五台发动机 他们想开始加速
As the vehicle went supersonic at about mach 1.2, it developed aerodynamic instability.
当飞行器以1.2马赫的速度进入超音速状态时 出现了气动力不稳的现象
They lost control of the vehicle, shut down the engines.
他们失去了对飞行器的控制 关闭了发动机
And that was the end.
就这样结束了
It was only two flights for this vehicle even although it was designed to be reusable.
这架飞行器只进行了两次飞行 尽管它的设计是可以重复使用的
So their third engine was the BE-3 and they switched over to hydrogen.
所以他们的第三台发动机是BE-3 改用了液氢
So hydrogen's a cryogenic propellant and it's very difficult to work with.
那么液氢是一种非常难用的低温推进剂
SpaceX has not developed a hydrogen engine internally.
SpaceX内部并没有开发出液氢发动机
They also chose an engine design that nobody else had managed to fly.
蓝色起源还选择了一种别人没试飞过的发动机设计
It's called the combustion tap off cycle.
这叫做抽气循环
So in a regular rocket engine you need to power those turbo pumps with hot gas
那么在普通的火箭发动机中 你需要用热气为那些涡轮泵提供动力
and you'll typically have a pre-burner or a gas generator that generates this.
你通常会有一个预燃烧器 或者气体发生器 来产生这些热气
So you've got a second combustion chamber.
那么这样就需要第二个燃烧室
But in the tap off cycle,
但在抽气循环中
they just say well why not just have a pipe that drains high pressure gas from the combustion chamber
他们只是说 为什么不干脆有一个管道 从燃烧室排出高压气体
and uses that to run the turbine
并利用它来运行涡轮机
so you get rid of some stuff.
那么这样可以去除一些部件
So in theory the engine is simpler and lighter.
所以理论上来说 发动机会更简单 更轻
Of course it's harder to build
当然 这种发动机其实更难制造
because you can't independently control the temperature for your turbines.
因为你无法独立控制涡轮的温度
It means it's much harder to get deep throttling.
这就意味着要想深度节流的话就难得多
And the BE-3 actually does have very good deep throttling capability.
而BE-3实际上有着非常好的深度节流能力
It's able to go from 100 percent down to below 20 percent.
它能够从100%节流到20%以下
And this means that unlike the Falcon 9
这意味着与猎鹰9号是不同的
which has to perform this hoverslam suicide burn by shutting down all but one of its nine engines
猎鹰9号是只启动一台发动机 来进行这种悬停猛击式的自杀式点火
this uses the same single engine on the way up and way down.
而新谢泼德上升和下降的过程中使用相同的单台发动机
It can throttle deeply enough that it can hover
它可以深度节流 推力小到足以在空中悬停
and slew across and land all back on the landing site.
并且水平飞行一段距离 然后着陆到着陆场
And it's not the only thing about New Shepard that makes it look like something you would build to get engineering experience.
除此之外 新谢泼德上还有一些特征是为了得到工程经验
The aerodynamics are very much different from any other vehicle I've seen.
它的气动力学外形与我见过的任何其他飞行器都有很大的不同
Obviously the booster has the capsule sitting on top.
很明显 助推器的顶部有一个载人舱
But once the capsule's gone it has this big annular ring-shaped fin
但一旦载人舱消失 就会变成一个大的环形翼面
and attached to that you see these air brakes that pop out during descent to control and slow things down.
附在上面的减速板在下降过程中会弹出 以控制并减慢速度
So that it has more controllable deceleration during return from space
这样它在从太空返回时的减速就更可控了
and a little extra braking during the landing procedure.
并在着陆过程中进行额外的制动
The capsule on top of course it detaches
在顶部的载人舱 当然就会分离出来
and it uses parachutes for its descent and ultimate landing.
并使用降落伞进行下降和最终的着陆
It has a small rocket engine that slows it down from like 15 miles an hour to five miles an hour
它有一个小型的火箭发动机 可以使速度从每小时24公里下降到每小时8公里
and there's also a ring of aluminium honeycomb crush core
而且还有一圈铝制蜂窝粉碎芯
so that if they hit too hard it will absorb a lot of the kinetic energy
这样如果他们撞得太狠 就会吸收很多动能
and avoid real damage to the capsule structure.
并避免对载人舱结构造成实际损害
Since the capsule is supposed to be a crew vehicle
由于载人舱应该是一个载人飞行器
it comes with a launch escape system
所以它带有发射逃逸系统
which will push the capsule away from the booster if anything goes wrong.
如果出了问题 它将把载人舱推离助推器
This escape motor is not built by Blue Origin.
这个逃逸发动机不是蓝色起源制造的
The escape motor as I understand it comes from Aerojet Rocketdyne.
据我所知 逃逸发动机来自阿罗杰特洛克达因公司
It's a high thrust solid rocket motor that can be replaced.
这是一个可以更换的推力大的固体火箭发动机
If you look inside the capsule, there's a sort of a plinth that comes up in the middle of the vehicle.
如果你看载人舱内部 有一个像是基座的东西 在航天器的中间
That's where the rocket motor is.
那就是火箭发动机的位置
So the capsule can escape at max q
那么载人舱可以在最大气动压力的状态下逃逸
that was the demonstration here and perform a safe return to the the earth.
正如这里的验证发射的画面一样 并安全返回地球
Now the booster in that case they were not sure whether the booster would survive
那么在这种情况下 他们不确定助推器是否能扛下来
because the boosters going at transonic speeds under full power
因为助推器发动机正以全功率的状态运行在跨音速阶段
and the aerodynamics are obviously changing at that moment.
而空气动力学显然在那一刻发生了变化
they fully expected that there was a pretty good chance the booster would be destroyed.
他们完全可以预料到 助推器有相当大的可能会被摧毁
It would either flip out a control or perhaps the rocket motor might damage the front of the vehicle
火箭要么会失控 要么会被载人舱的固体火箭损坏前面的部分
and that would develop into something worse.
那会变得更糟
But no. The booster performed this wonderful deceleration, descent
但是没有 助推器很好地进行了减速和下降的过程
and landing back where it was supposed to
并落回了它应该着陆的地方
which is good job team.
他们团队做得不错啊
Now there is a second version of the BE-3, the BE-3U
那么BE-3有了第二个版本 BE-3U
which is going to be the second stage of the New Glenn rocket.
这将是新格伦火箭的二级
And the U means upper stage obviously.
而U显然是指上面级
The engine design instead using the combustion tap off, it's an expander cycle.
发动机的设计 不是抽气循环 而是膨胀循环
An expander cycles, you take the very cold liquid hydrogen.
膨胀循环是指 你把非常冷的液氢
You run it over heat exchanger so it takes heat from the combustion
通过热交换器 这样就能从燃烧室获得热量
and it wants to vaporize
使之蒸发
and that's allowed to expand through the turbine which drives the pumps
并通过驱动泵的涡轮机进行膨胀
and you get a pretty high performance engine from this.
然后从中得到一个性能相当高的发动机
So this is similar to the RL-10 engine that's already used on the upper stage of Atlas and Delta IV.
那么 这与宇宙神和德尔塔四上面级已经使用的RL-10发动机类似
But it's an open cycle version
但这是一个开式循环的版本
so it's not as efficient but it gets a lot more thrust.
所以它的效率不高 但推力更大
So while New Glenn is going to use these for its second stage
所以 当新格伦打算用这些东西来做第二级的时候
the Vulcan built by ULA is going to stick to the RL-10
ULA制造的火神火箭将坚持使用RL-10
but both rockets are going to use the BE-4 engines which have been developed by Blue Origin
但这两枚火箭都将使用蓝色起源研发的BE-4发动机(作为一级发动机)
and this is a staged combustion cycle methane engine.
而这是一个分级燃烧循环的甲烷发动机
It gets more thrust than the Raptor but it's not a full flow.
它的推力比猛禽大 但不是全流量分级燃烧循环
Let's be clear.
明确地说
It's just a regular staged combustion cycle getting great thrust and great performance.
这只是一个普通的分级燃烧循环 有着巨大的推力和强大的性能
So if all goes according to plan
所以如果一切按计划进行
we should see two of these powering the first flight of Vulcan later this year.
今年晚些时候 我们应该能看到其中的两台为火神火箭的首飞提供动力
And we should see seven of these powering New Glenn.
而我们应该看到7个这样的发动机为新格伦提供动力
Now officially New Glenn is supposed to fly 2021.
那么新格伦应该在2021年正式飞行
I'm skeptical of that.
我对此持怀疑态度
Because they've had trouble with delivering the engines on time for ULA's Vulcan
因为他们在为ULA的火神火箭按时交付发动机方面遇到了麻烦
and that's been pushed out to the fourth quarter of 2021.
而这已经被推到了2021年第四季度
It's entirely possible this has shifted to next year.
这完全有可能已经推移到了明年
But it would certainly be an ambitious vehicle.
但它肯定会是一个艰巨的火箭
It would be able to put more mass into low earth orbit than Falcon 9.
它的近地轨道运载质量比猎鹰9号更大
On paper it wouldn't be as capable as Falcon Heavy
在纸面上 它的运力不如重型猎鹰
but then again this has a much larger fairing
但同样地 它的整流罩更大
and Falcon Heavy is definitely limited by its fairing size.
而重型猎鹰绝对会受限于整流罩尺寸
The first stage is supposed to be completely reusable.
一级应该是可以完全重复使用的
Has seven engines
拥有七台发动机
but it should only need one of those engines to get the thrust to mass ratio required for a landing.
但应该只需要一台发动机就能获得着陆所需的推重比
They've actually acquired ships which are old car ferries I think
他们其实已经收购了一些船 我觉得这些船是旧的汽车渡轮
which they're in the process of adapting into floating landing pads.
他们正准备将其改造成浮动的着陆场
Of course I'm saying this in the week after
当然 我是在那件事发生一周后说的这句话
it's been revealed that SpaceX has bought a pair of old oil drilling platforms
那件事就是SpaceX已经买下了一对旧的石油钻井平台
and plan to use those with Starship.
并计划将其用于Starship
They are going to be called Phobos and Deimos.
它们将被称为福波斯和得摩斯
And you guys are getting way too excited about an eccentric billionaire
你们对一个古怪的亿万富翁太兴奋了
Phobos意为害怕，Deimos意为恐惧
who now owns a pair of offshore bases named fear and dread.
他现在拥有一对名为害怕 和恐惧 的离岸基地
指命名应该是根据火星的卫星，也就是希腊神话，而不是这俩词的本意来命名的
Yeah you guys should really be keeping up with your classical mythology
是啊 你们真的应该跟上你们的古典神话了
But anyway there's one other rocket engine that Blue Origin has developed
但不管怎么说 蓝色起源还研发了一款火箭发动机
And it's the BE-7 which is designed for landing stuff on the moon.
那就是为登陆月球而设计的BE-7
It's another hydrogen engine.
这是另一种液氢发动机
It's got deep throttle control. Uses the expander cycle.
它使用膨胀循环 可以深度节流
I think it's like a smaller and more efficient version of the BE-3U.
我认为它就像BE-3U的一个更小更高效的版本
And it's one of Blue Origin's core contributions to the National Team
这也是蓝色起源对国家队 (月球着陆器)的核心贡献之一
which has made a bid for the Human Landing System or the Artemis Program.
也就是为阿尔忒弥斯计划中的载人登月系统(HLS)竞标的方案
They're one of three finalists
他们是三个入围者之一
and there is supposed to be a downselect decision made early this year
而今年年初应该会淘汰掉一个方案
but I won't be surprised if that gets pushed out
但如果HLS被砍了 我也不会惊讶
since Congress hasn't really delivered the amount of money needed.
因为国会还没有真正划出其所需的资金量
And the primary driver behind the accelerated timeline is well no longer in the white house.
而加速的时间表背后的主要推动者已经不在白宫了
But long before humans return to the surface of the moon
但早在人类重返月球表面之前
Blue Origin is probably going to put stuff stuff on the surface using Blue Moon which is their lander
蓝色起源可能会用蓝月亮 也就是他们的着陆器 把东西放在月表上
And that's part of NASA's commercial lunar payload services program or CLPS.
那是NASA商业月球有效载荷服务项目的一部分 简称CLPS
So yeah they can put payloads on this.
所以是的 他们可以把有效载荷放在这上面
Take them to the surface.
把它们带到月表
They could be rovers experiments other hardware.
可以是漫游车 实验品 其他设备等等
And that is powered again by the BE-7 engine.
而这也是由BE-7发动机提供动力的
In fact the National Team's lander. It's essentially an extension of the Blue Moon spacecraft.
事实上 国家队的登陆器 它本质上是蓝月亮航天器的延伸
So that is the state of Blue Origin right now
那么这就是蓝色起源现在的状态
and many people point out they haven't been quite as aggressive or as fast as SpaceX
而许多人指出 他们还没有像SpaceX那样激进或快速
but then again they haven't exploded as many rockets as SpaceX.
但话又说回来了 他们没有像SpaceX那样炸过很多火箭
As far as I'm concerned they can take as long as they like
在我看来 他们想花多长时间就花多长时间
as long as they don't go out of businesses
只要不倒闭就行
as long as they keep building rockets, they'll be interesting to look at.
只要他们继续制造火箭 关注他们就很有趣
And it will be a fantastic moment
而这将是一个美妙的时刻
when paying members of the public can look at some of this hardware from the inside.
当为此花费的公众可以从内部看到这些设备的一些情况
And look down on the earth below them.
并看向着陆器下方的地面
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]